Michael Racanelli MSc.

Oakville ON | (+1) 519-281-1284

m.v.racanelli@gmail.com - LinkedIn - GitHub - Portfolio

Published Medical Scientist and certified Data Scientist with two years experience working as a member of a global oncology clinical data analytic team for a major pharmaceutical corporation. Years of experience working in other pharmaceutical functions including Clinical Research, Medical Affairs and Clinical Data Analytics. Strong translational skills to unify medical domain knowledge with developer operations and communication skills to convey complex concepts to a broad audience.

EDUCATION

Certification of Data Science
Master of Medical Science
Bachelor of Medical Science (Honours)

University of Toronto/University of Waterloo – 2023 Western University – 2019 Western University – 2016

SKILLS

Development – Python, R, SAS, Git, Bash **Data Management** – Pandas, Pyspark, Jupyter Notebooks/Databricks, Azure Data Factory **Interactive Dashboards** – Shiny, Streamlit, Bohek, Plotly, PowerBI **Machine Learning** –Scikit-Learn, TensorFlow, Keras, LLM API integration

WORK EXPERIENCE

Clinical Data Analyst, Full-time – Current Role

April 2023 – Present

Bayer Inc, Mississauga

- Built, deployed, and maintained custom dashboards to visualize patient data, using internal APIs to empower users to design their own plots using Large Language Models
- Manage and transform data using Pyspark within data pipelines, collaborating with a global team to power visual dashboards used for clinical decision-making
- Created interactive documentation/ tutorials for internal oncology data pipeline to create a SQL database used in drug submissions to health authorities that identifies on and off target genetic mutations

Scientific Analyst QA, Permanent Full-time

May 2022 – August 2022

BenchSci, Toronto, Ontario

- Supported and coordinated across multiple teams regular QA initiatives and onboarding with new QA software to assess platform quality and function with each platform and data release
- Provided scientific expertise for coding test cases and bug reporting in collaboration with software QA team

Local Study Associate, Contract Full-time

February 2020 - May 2021

Bayer Inc, Mississauga, Ontario

• Managed Bayer Sponsored and Investigator Sponsored Medical Research studies according to global guidelines and regulations (ICH-GCP), specialized in Oncology and Hematology

Laboratory Research Assistant and Thesis Student Laboratory of Dr. A. Leask, London, Ontario	September 2016 – July 2019
Teaching Assistant, Physiology/ Pharmacology Lab Course Western University, London, Ontario	September 2017 – May 2018
Dental School Simulation Clinic Supervisor	December 2016 – March 2018
Schulich School of Medicine and Dentistry, London, Ontario	
Collection Clerk, Financial Services – Summer Student	May 2015 – September 2015
Bayer Inc., Mississauga, Ontario	
Medical Operations Business Associate – Summer Student	May 2013 – September 2013
GlaxoSmithKline, Mississauga, Ontario	May 2012 – September 2012

Shi-Wen, X., Racanelli, M., Ali, A., Simon, A., Quesnel, K., Stratton, R. J., & Leask, A. (2021). **Verteporfin inhibits the persistent fibrotic phenotype of lesional scleroderma dermal fibroblasts**. Journal of cell communication and signaling, 15(1), 71–80. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12079-020-00596-x

Racanelli M, (2019). YAP-mediated mechanotransduction promotes fibrotic activity. *Electronic Thesis and Dissertation Repository*. 6283. https://ir.lib.uwo.ca/etd/6283

Hutchenreuther, J., Vincent, K., Norley, C., Racanelli, M., Gruber, S. B., Johnson, T. M., Fullen, D. R., Raskin, L., Perbal, B., Holdsworth, D. W., Postovit, L. M., & Leask, A. (2018). **Activation of cancer-associated fibroblasts is required for tumor neovascularization in a murine model of melanoma**. Matrix biology: journal of the International Society for Matrix Biology, 74, 52–61. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.matbio.2018.06.003

LICENSES & CERTIFICATIONS

PUBLICATIONS

Data Science Certification	December 2023
University of Waterloo/Toronto	
Machine Learning, Data Science and Deep Learning with Python	November 2021
Udemy	
Complete Python Developer in 2021: Zero to Mastery	September 2021
Udemy	
Study Designs in Epidemiology	January 2021
Coursera	
Al for Everyone	November 2019
Coursera	